Sam B. Hall, Jr. Papers, Inclusive: 1943-2005, undated Bulk: 1976-1985
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Sam B. Hall, Jr. Papers
Inclusive: 1943-2005, undated Bulk: 1976-1985
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
48
Hall, Sam B., Jr.
529 document boxes 15 binder boxes 4 flat OVZ boxes
The Sam B. Hall, Jr. papers are focused on the period in which he served as a United States House Representative (1976-1985). Materials present include correspondence, campaign materials, subject files, project files, and research materials. Other items include schedules, itineraries, committee materials, radio transcripts and speeches, and audiovisual materials. Materials from his time as a Federal Judge are also present (1985-1994).
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Sam Blakely Hall, Jr. was born in Marshall, Harrison County, Texas, on January 11, 1924. He graduated from Marshall High School in 1940 and obtained an Associate of Arts degree from the College of Marshall (now East Texas Baptist University) in 1942. He then began studying law at the University of Texas.
As most young men did during the time, Hall joined the military and served in the Army Air Corps from 1943-1945. After his service, he enrolled in the Baylor School of Law and graduated in 1948. Soon after he began to practice in his hometown of Marshall, Texas and did so until 1976.
In 1962 Sam Hall opposed Wright Patman in the Democratic primary to represent the 1st Congressional District but was defeated. Upon Patman’s death in 1976, Hall won a special election and began his tenure as a United States Congressional Representative. He attributed this, and five re-elections, to a strong standing in the local community.
During the 94th Legislature Hall served on the Education and Labor Committee as well as the Science and Technology Committee. From the 95th to the 99th Legislatures he served on the Judiciary and Veteran’s Affairs Committees and the Select Committee on Narcotics Abuse and Control. While on the Judiciary Committee he also served on subcommittees including Criminal Justice; Immigration, Refugees, and International Law; and Administrative Law and Governmental Relations which he chaired from 1982-1984.
As a Congressman Hall traveled with several CODELS, or Congressional Delegations to international locales including Lebanon, Germany, France, and Southeast Asia. His travel corresponded with the work he was doing while on the Judiciary and Veterans’ Affairs Committees and the Select Committee on Narcotics Abuse and Control.
Representative Hall was a conservative Texas Democrat. As such, he was one of the founding members of the “Boll Weevils”, southern Democrats who often sided with Republicans on national issues. Hall was also a supporter of President Ronald Reagan and his economic plans. This relationship with the Reagan led to Hall’s appointment as a federal judge.
In 1985 President Reagan nominated Sam Hall as United States District judge for the Eastern District of Texas. His continued interest in the law, and work on the House Judiciary Committee, kept Hall in contact with the skills needed as a judge. Hall was confirmed as District Judge May 3, 1985, which led to his resignation from the United States House of Representatives on May 27, 1985. He served in this capacity until his death, April 10, 1994.
Sam Hall was married to the former Madeleine Segal and had three daughters: Becky, Amanda, and Sandra. The United States Courthouse and Federal Building in Marshall, Texas is named in his honor.
Scope and Content
The Sam B. Hall, Jr. papers are focused on the period in which he served as a United States House Representative (1976-1985). Materials from his time as a Federal Judge are also present (1985-1994).
The Campaigns series includes items from several parts of the congressional campaign process. Sam Hall faced redistricting while in office, therefore maps and census data used to analyze a new potential district are included in the Redistricting subseries. The Democrats subseries includes Whip Advisories and information provided by the Democratic Study Group, and the Elections subseries includes results, correspondence, advertisements, and official documents filed for election purposes.
The Committees series is divided into five subseries including committee and subcommittee work. The General subseries includes material collected regarding Hall’s general interests and not his specific committees; topics include appropriations, agriculture, banking and finance, foreign affairs, and ways and means. The other four subseries cover his work on the Judiciary and Veterans’ Affairs Committees and the Select Committees on Narcotics Abuse Control and Ethics.
As a native to the district he served, Congressman Hall was closely involved in the community. The Constituents, District, and Events series document his work and appearances. Alpha files and project files can be found as well as correspondence and invitations to various events. Restricted files are included in the District series.
The Judicial series includes items regarding the 1980 Reagan budget, however the bulk of materials is concentrated on Hall’s time as a federal judge. The Legislative series, in addition to the Committees series, make up the bulk of this collection. Legislative papers include bills, correspondence, Dear Colleague letters, program, and project files. Significant legislation in the files includes the Soft Drink Act, Hobbs Act, Simpson-Mazzoli Immigration Reform and Control Act, Immigration and Naturalization Act, and the Vietnamese refugee resettlement bills.
Newsletters, press releases, and radio transcripts can be found in the Press series. The radio transcripts correspond with the reel to reels and cassette tapes found in the Audio-Visual series. The Photographs, Albums, and Scrapbooks series includes visual materials collected throughout Hall’s congressional career. Most of the items are evidence of his work visiting the 1st Congressional district as well as hosting constituents and dignitaries in DC. Travel photos are also included.
Arrangement
The Sam B. Hall, Jr. papers were originally processed and described in 1990. A secondary finding aid was created in 1995 to include further description and additional materials acquired after completion of the original finding aid.
The current arrangement has been updated to better align items topically, which led to the restructuring of the original series. There are now fourteen series, most of which have subseries and several with sub-subseries. The series are: Campaigns; Committees; Constituents; District; Events; Executive; Judicial; Legislative; Personal; Press; Trips; Voting Record; Audio-Visual; Photographs, Albums, and Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 48. Acquired 1986-06-23
Related Resources
Related references
Hall, Sam Blakeley, Jr.” Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. Accessed June 9, 2015.
Sam B. Hall, Jr. papers, Accession #48, Box #477b, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Hall, Sam B. (Sam Blakeley), 1924-1994 -- Archives -- Indexes.
Subjects (Organizations)
Democratic Party (Tex.); United States. Congress. House -- Elections.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Veterans' Affairs.; United States. Congress. House. Select Committee on Ethics.; United States. Congress. House. Select Committee on Narcotics and Abuse Control.; United States. Congress. House.
Subjects
Agriculture -- United States.; Apportionment (Election law) -- Texas.; Finance--United States.; International relations -- United States.; Judges -- United States.; Legislators -- United States -- Archives.; Newsletters.; Political campaigns -- Texas.; Politicians -- Texas.
Genres
Albums (Books); Appointment Books.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Interviews.; Invitations.; Legislative materials.; Maps.; Open reel audiotapes.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Programs (Publications).; Records (Documents); Speeches.; VHS.
- Campaigns, 1976-1984, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Campaigns series has been divided into three subseries, Redistricting, Democrats, and Elections, and documents the elections in which Hall participated from 1976-1984.
  The Redistricting subseries contains correspondence, news clippings, and oversized maps related to the 1980 census and subsequent rearrangement of Hall’s congressional district. Materials show the potential losses and gains that could affect the elections. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
  The Democrats subseries is organized chronologically from 1980-1984. It houses reports from the Democratic Study Group (DSG), Whip Advisories, and items from the Democratic Caucus and Democratic National Committee.
  The Elections subseries is further divided by election year: 1976, 1978, 1980, 1982, and 1984. Each sub-subseries includes information on opponents, results, news clippings, campaign advertising, and correspondence.
  - Redistricting, 1979-1982; 1
    - Texas Senate Redistricting Committee Material (1 of 3), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Texas Senate Redistricting Committee Material (2 of 3), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Texas Senate Redistricting Committee Material (3 of 3), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - News clippings, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Legal Documents, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Office Memos, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Redistricting and Census Maps (1 of 4), 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Redistricting and Census Maps (2 of 4), 1980-1982 (Box 525 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Redistricting and Census Maps (3 of 4), 1980-1982 (Box 525 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - Redistricting and Census Maps (4 of 4), 1980-1982 (Box 525 OVZ, Folder 3)
    - Census Correspondence (1 of 2), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Census Correspondence (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Redistricting Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Census/Redistricting News clippings, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Democrats, 1980-1984, undated; 2
    - Campaign Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Reports and Legislative Programs, 1980 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Legislative Reports, 1980 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Daily Reports. Legislative Programs, 1980 July (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Legislative Reports, 1980 August (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Daily Reports and Legislative Programs, 1980 August (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Legislative Report, Schedule for Week, 1980 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Special Report, Gramm — Latta II, 1980 July 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Fact Sheet, Reconciliation Conference Report, 1981 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Fact Sheet, Caribbean Basin Initiative, 1983 July 8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Fact Sheet, Covert and Cutoff, 1983 July 15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Democratic Study Group (DSG) Fact Sheet, Superfund Extension, 1984 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Whip Advisory, 1980 June (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Whip Advisory, 1980 July (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Whip Advisory, 1980 August (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Whip Advisory, 1981 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 98th Democratic Congress, 1982 December 6-9 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1980 Democratic National Convention (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Democratic National Committee, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Democratic National Committee, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Democratic Caucus, Committee on Organization, Study, and Review (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Democratic Caucus, Committee on Organization, Study, and Review (2 of 2), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Democratic Caucus, Crime Package, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Democratic Caucus, Committee on Organization, Study and Review. Meeting agenda and material (particularly concern rules), 1984 November 19 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Democratic Caucus, Correspondence and printed material (1 of 2), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Democratic Caucus, Correspondence and printed material (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1976-1984, undated; 3
    - 1976, 1976-1977; 1
      - Advertisement cards, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Possible issues during campaign (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Possible issues during campaign (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Positions, circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Special Election Certificate, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Election Results, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - General Election, 1976 November 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Democrat Position Papers, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Primary, 1976 May 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Fred Hudson, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Gordon Wills, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Dr. James Hogan, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - James Allison, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - March, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Mrs. James Davis, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - John E. Wade, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Welby Parish, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - George Preston, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Jesse Nickerson, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - List of Newspapers and Sample Press Release, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Current Newspaper clippings, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - General, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Jim Wright, Correspondence, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Financial Register, 1977 (Box 525 OVZ, Folder 4)
    - 1978, 2
      - Fred Hudson, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Fred Hudson Voting Changes, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Fred Hudson News Clippings, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Advertising (Correspondence, etc.), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - General Election, Advertising messages, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - General Election, results, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Campaign Activity, information (ethics), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Democratic National Committee, Legislative Analysis, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - General Election, Voting Results, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Democratic Primary, Results, 1978 May 6 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Congratulations Letters, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - General Primary, Letters of Congratulations, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - General Primary, Newspapers Clippings, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1980, 3
      - Re-Election Campaign posters, circa 1980 (Box 525 OVZ, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, Press Releases, Legal Documents, Announcement for re-election, 1980 January 5 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - News clippings, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - General Primary results, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Democratic Primary, County and District Races, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Congratulatory Letters, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - General Election Results, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1982, 4
      - General Election Precinct Results, John Taylor, Opponent, 1982 November 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - General Election Results, 1982 (Box 8a, Folder 1)
      - Primary Results, 1982 (Box 8a, Folder 2)
      - Primary, Advertising and Media Coverage, News clippings, 1982 (Box 8a, Folder 3)
      - Notice of Re-election, Correspondence, Legal Documents, Press Releases, 1982 (Box 8a, Folder 4)
    - 1984, 1984, undated; 5
      - Announcement for Re-election. Correspondence, Press Releases, Legal Documents, 1984 (Box 8a, Folder 5)
      - Democratic Primary Results, 1984 May 5 (Box 8a, Folder 6)
      - News clippings, 1984 (Box 8a, Folder 7)
      - Results, 1984 (Box 8a, Folder 8)
      - Congratulations, 1984 (Box 8a, Folder 9)
      - Hall for Congress felt vests, undated (Box 524, Folder 1)
- Committees, 1964-1985; 2
  The Committees series has five subseries: General, Judiciary Committee, Select Committee on Narcotics Abuse and Control, Select Committees on Ethics, and Veterans Affairs Committee, dated 1964-1985.
  The General subseries holds committee and subcommittee materials collected by Hall’s office from 1982-1985. While Hall was not on most of these committees, their inclusion provides insight into the various interests of Hall while in Congress. This subseries is organized chronologically by topic.
  The Judiciary Committee, Select Committee on Narcotics and Abuse Control, Select Committee on Ethics, and Veterans Affairs Committees subseries are reflective of Congressman Hall’s committee work while in office. His membership from 1976-1985 was active and challenging as it presented significant and often controversial reform legislation.
  Hall’s work on the Judiciary Committee is further divided to document his time on the full committee as well as the Immigration Subcommittee, Criminal Justice Subcommittee, and Administrative Law and Governmental Relations subcommittee. Hall was chairman of the Administrative Law and Governmental Relations Subcommittee from 1983-1985. Items of note include criminal code reform (Criminal Justice Subcommittee, 1978-1981), immigration reform (also known as the Simpson-Mazzoli Bill, Immigration Subcommittee, 1981-85), and regulatory reform (Administration and Government Operation Subcommittee, 1983-1985).
  - General, 1964-1985; 1
    - Money Facts, Subcommittee on Domestic Finance, Committee on Banking and Currency, 1964 September 21 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Comptroller General of the U.S. Program Report, 1973-1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Draft of CBO Budget Issue Paper, 1976 January 4 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Suggested remarks by Mr. Cacioppo, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Clerk of the House, Correspondence, pm, 1977-1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - House Administration Committee, Correspondence, pm, 1977-1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Appropriations, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Appropriations, Subcommittees on Public Works, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Menu, House Restaurant, 1978 September 14 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Office of the Doorkeeper-C, pm, 1978-1984 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Jurisdiction, Correspondence, pm, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Legislative Profile, 1979 January 15-September 29 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Automatic dissemination of Legislative status information, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - House Restaurant, Financial Records, Correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Appropriations Committee, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Appropriations Committee, Subcommittee on Agriculture, Rural Development, and Related Agencies, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Appropriations Committee, Subcommittee on Foreign Operation, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Appropriations Committee, Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Development - Independent Agencies, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Appropriations Committee, Subcommittee on Interior Appropriations, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Appropriations Committee, Subcommittee on Labor, Health, and Human Services, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Armed Service Committee, Subcommittee on Investigations, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Armed Service Committee, Subcommittee on Military Installations and Facilities, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Armed Service Committee, Subcommittee on Readiness, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs Committee, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs Committee, Subcommittee on Financial Institutions, Supervision, Regulation, and Insurance, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Congress, Subcommittee on Federal Charters, 1982 August 18 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Unofficial list of members, 98th Congress, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Aging, Health and Long Term, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Agriculture (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Agriculture (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Agriculture, Cotton, Rice, and Sugar, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Agriculture, Forests, Family Farms, and Energy, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Agriculture, Tobacco and Peanuts, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Agriculture, Livestock, Dairy, & Poultry (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Agriculture, Livestock, Dairy, and Poultry (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Appropriations (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Appropriations (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Appropriations, Agriculture, Rural Development, and Related Agencies (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Appropriations, Agriculture, Rural Development and Related Agencies (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Appropriations, Defense (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Appropriations, Defense (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Appropriations, Energy and Water Development, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Appropriations, Foreign Operations, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Appropriations, Housing and Urban Development-Independent Agencies, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Appropriations, Interior, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Appropriations, Labor, Health and Human Services, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Appropriations, Labor, Health and Human Services and Education, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Appropriations, Treasury, Postal Service, General Government, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Armed Services (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Armed Services (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Armed Services, Investigations, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Armed Services, Military Installations and Facilities, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Armed Services, Military Personnel and Compensation, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Armed Services, Procurement and Military Nuclear Systems, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Armed Services, Readiness, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, Consumer Affairs and Coinage, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, Financial Institutions, Supervision, Regulation, and Insurance (1 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, Financial Institutions, Supervision, Regulation, and Insurance (2 of 2), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, Housing and Community Development, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, International Development, Institutions and Finance, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs, International Trade Investment and Monetary Policy, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Budget, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Comments of the State of the Union Address, 1983 January 25 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Education and Labor, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Education and Labor, Human Resources, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 21)